<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Trip Inside a Separate Mind</title>
    <description>Blog with band news, history, songwriting, and bullshit</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 13:55:11 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 13:55:11 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Songwriting - The Wakening</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are no lyrics, of course, but no discussion of the first Death Beast album would be complete without discussing the creation of the introduction track “The Wakening”. Would you call an intro a ‘title track’? I don’t think of it as such, and to be honest I just think of it as ‘the intro’ because I didn’t really realize it when titling it that I had already used “The Wakening” as a song title before - for the acoustic+lead guitar intro to the song “Soulsword” from Rampage’s “Bellum Infinitum” album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title “The Wakening” came from some AIM discussions between me and Stan when we were coming up with ideas for songs and the album. Between the two of us we came up with the idea of doing at least three albums, and then naming them in sequence - “The Wakening”, “The Onslaught”, and “The Aftermath” - with the sequence of themes being obvious. And, in looking at the lyrics Stan wrote for the first album, he certainly held up his end of the bargain - every song has some kind of an ‘impending doom’ or ‘your destruction is on the way’ kind of feel to it, and it’s what I tried to keep up with on “The Onslaught” by making the destruction not impending but active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, instead of just blasting out of the gate on the first album, I knew I wanted to do some kind of intro, but clean guitars/acoustics weren’t the right feel and keyboards would not work, so I thought I’d go with some kind of lead guitar/guitar effects track - not actual music plus solos, but just noisemaking that had some kind of rhyme and reason to it. Aimless noodling wasn’t going to cut it, but a riff with solos would be too structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the same tool that helped me with layering backing vocals and the sound effects at the end of “Here Comes the War” ended up working perfectly - Sonic Foundry’s “Acid” looper. I had plenty of practice by doing the layering vocals for songs, whether just putting multiple vocal tracks together and in-sync or doing the more elaborate ‘growing army of the dead’ bit at the end of “Enslaved Cadavers”. I saw how I could add multiple tracks and mix them, and even mix single song-length tracks with looped repeating soundbytes, so I sat down and banged it all out in one evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start was the feedback - I just hit ‘record’ and held my guitar up to the computer speakers which were monitoring the amp and started that nice, clean feedback. I did a bit of gradually moving it back and forth for a touch of volume swelling, but basically just let it feed back for close to two minutes, at which point I pulled back all the way to stop and I left that as the first ‘base’ track. Next I laid down a second track of me recording in stereo a Slayer-esque cacophony of random chromatic picking, trills, pinch harmonics, whammy bar dives… I put Kerry King’s entire guitar &lt;em&gt;oeuvre&lt;/em&gt; from the first three Slayer albums into two minutes. Then, for a more fucked-up sound, I edited that stereo track in Sound Forge by taking one of the two channels and just reversing it completely - that way, instead of one stereo noise track, I had two completely different noise tracks panned hard-left/hard-right with one of them sounding ‘off’ by being backwards. Then, for even more of a cacophonous sound, I recorded another guitar track of me doing high unison bends, bending both to perfect pitch and just a bit flat, kinda like Quorthon’s leads on the song “Blood Fire Death”. I just stayed on the one note through the whole track, then I edited it by fading up at the start and down at the end, and I auto-set the pan to slowly take it from center to hard-left, then slowly to hard-right, and just slowly back and forth until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mixing that together left me with something cacophonous and nearly amorphous, but with JUST enough structure to not be pointless. I still felt it needed something, though, and that’s when thinking back again to the “Enslaved Cadavers” outro gave me the idea to add more horror to it by adding some vocals. I started going back to the other vocal tracks on the album and cutting out particularly good screams and shouts. Then, I would make copies of them and start playing with them - pitch-shift up, or pitch-shift down, or reversing them, or leaving them in stereo and swapping phase so they sound bizarre, and just pasting those in. Then I started cutting out a couple of vocal lines and adding those, also manipulated in the same ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then another idea hit me and I started recording some spoken lines - I’d say things like ‘death beast’ or ‘hell’ or other random words or short phrases from the lyrics. Some of these I would just slow down and paste in. Others I would reverse and put in backwards. On a couple, I reversed the line just to hear what it sounded like backwards, then I recorded myself speaking them by phonetically trying to copy the backwards speech, then reversing that fake-reverse to get something that sounded forward, but ‘off’. I also recorded one little ‘secret’ in there, pitch shifted WAY down and reversed - the cat’s out of the bag on that one so it’s not really ‘secret’ anymore, but I wonder if anyone picked it out back at the time, or will bother doing so now. Do people still try to play their metal albums backwards for the hidden messages?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/songs/songwriting-the-wakening</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/songs/songwriting-the-wakening</guid>
        
        <category>Death-Beast</category>
        
        <category>The-Wakening</category>
        
        
        <category>Songs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyrics - Here Comes the War</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Between the two emails of lyrics from Dementor we had lyrics for eight Death Beast songs, which I had counted as enough for our first album. But, as it turned out, I ended up writing another one - “Here Comes the War”. This one was unique in that, unlike other Death Beast songs but like many of my Rampage songs, I wrote the music first. In fact, I didn’t even have any lyrics or title for it - just an idea of the feel that I wanted, which was something in “F#”. Actually E, since I tune down a whole step, but you know what I mean - rooted in the thrash tradition of the root being on the second fret, and getting the 7th-root movement by hammering on from open to 2nd fret, something like “Trapped Under Ice”, the pre-chorus to “South of Heaven”, or the main riff to the song “Exodus”. In fact, that song was literally the inspiration for it, to the point that the original filename for it was “xodus_fl.sng” - “Exodus-feel song”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stumbled across the main riff while trying to write something like the verse riff of “Exodus”, 7th-to-root by hammering on and then going to the tritone for accents, but tweaked it with the hammer-pull-off riff to get its own flavor. A little more playing got me to the descending chromatics for the chorus parts, but I tried to break up the samey-ness by making one repeat a whole step higher and going from straight-8th-based descents to 3-on-2 triplets. I also stepped up the solo sections another whole step and put each solo section a fourth apart, going A-B-A-Harmony for the soloists (another nod to Dark Angel’s “Death is Certain”, which uses the same solo arrangement - I’ve done that quite a bit, now that I think about it…), and then a ‘chorus riff’ with just vocal screams and solos instead of a fully-sung chorus. Again, all pretty standard, but I tried to change a few things to give it a bit of a different feel. When I sent the last set of music to Stan for his ill-fated final vocal sessions (the ones where Dementor’s computer blew up and he ended up deciding to quit Death Beast) I sent this one along, asking him to try to come up with a title and write one more song’s worth of lyrics for it. I don’t know if he ever did write anything, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally got Ramrod to join Death Beast he heard the instrumental version of it and liked it. We were chatting on AIM and he said he already had an idea for it - the title would be “Here Comes the War”, and that would be repeated in the chorus. He said he’d need a bit to come up with the lyrics, though. Just before Ramrod joined, though, I had asked Aerik to join Death Beast on vocals. He declined, as he was already singing for Rampage and didn’t want to have it sound the same, but he wasn’t opposed to writing lyrics for me. Well, Ramrod was also working with Aerik on the Von Frankensteins and so the two of them put their heads together for lyrics on “Here Comes the War”, and of course by now you all know what they came up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Feel the heat, the burning streets as bullets rape the air
The bombs will fly and men will die and nobody will care
But empty heads obsessed with death just so afraid to die
A protest here – just built on fear and tears the cowards cry
But in the trench or on the bench the others hide from heroes ends
Insurgents rise to spite the lives of a reign come to an end
Roadside bombs like horrid songs explode with living hell
The war still lost, but keeps the costs of lives where soldiers fell

Here comes the Pain - Here comes the War
Drives you insane - Here comes the war
Pray for your death - Here comes the war
Take your last breath - Here comes the war

The flag is torn, weakened and worn being burned by those we &quot;saved&quot;
The soilders grind against the tide in lands that rest untamed
In the name of God, the killing dog who spurs them to attack
From friends to foes to silent death, the blade against the back
From desert sands, by foreign hands, the gates of hell tear free
Chemical war, the silent whore, may spread it's misery
We took the throne but now lay prone for the God and his mad slaves
The war won't end till all lay dead and rot in nameless graves

Here comes the Pain - Here comes the War
Drives you insane - Here comes the war
Pray for your death - Here comes the war
Take your last breath - Here comes the war

The tanks are burned, and overturned, the cities smoke and ash
To save the mind, the killing kind, false peace the aftermath
Our bitter mold, a social gold, forced down upon the tribe
A despot king to justice bring but we failed to save the lives
And now we're here, still torn by fear, fighting street to street
The war still hot, the &quot;peace&quot; that's not, but death you get to keep
The fire ceased – so soon released, the war will not subside
When soilders trained take on the rage it's the fate of man to die

Here comes the Pain - Here comes the War
Drives you insane - Here comes the war
Pray for your death - Here comes the war
Take your last breath - Here comes the war
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were perfect, and as such they never changed through Ryan’s fortunately-surviving demo version, the album version on &lt;em&gt;The Wakening&lt;/em&gt;, or any of the live versions after that. Swapping off the vocals on the live version was just a way to add some color to the live album as well as to pay tribute to Ramrod. The idea came from Desaster’s “Metalized Blood”, in the way that they had three guest vocalists to sing one each of the three verses. It’s a shame we didn’t get to do more writing together, because this one came together really easily and I think it’s one of the better songs from the first album.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/songs/lyrics-here-comes-the-war</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/songs/lyrics-here-comes-the-war</guid>
        
        <category>Death-Beast</category>
        
        <category>The-Wakening</category>
        
        
        <category>Songs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyrics - Invoking Villainy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The last song I wrote with Dementor for Death Beast, “Invoking Villainy”, was sent along with “Enslaved Cadavers” after we had already written the first six songs from that initial email. As with “Enslaved Cadavers” he never got a chance to record any vocals for it, so I wonder what he would have ultimately done. As it was, it was pretty sparse with only two short verses and two short choruses, plus a tag line, so I knew I’d have to add some more musical content somehow to get it to full-song length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Whispers turn to screams in the black mass
Orgies of fiends in the black mass
Sacrifice for sin in the black mass
Nothing is forbidden in the black mass

Invoking Villainy
Conjuring Devilry
Invoking Villainy
Black Mass Insanity

Scourging virgins in the black mass
Raping purity in the black mass
Only sinners survive the black mass
All others die in the black mass

Invoking Villainy
Conjuring Devilry
Invoking Villainy
Satanic Insanity

...the Black Mass!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constant repeats of ‘black mass’ at the end of each verse line, along with the very similar short vocal lines for the choruses, pointed to something that would lend itself to a chant-type of feel. As such, my options were to find exactly the right riff that would lend itself to repetition without being boring or to build something elaborate with a lot of musical sections and changes with just not that much singing. My first thought was the latter, and thus I started trying every kind of riff in the world, finding stuff I could build together to build a monster of a song - perhaps along the lines of “Live Undead” by Slayer, which was my first thought, or “No Love” by Exodus. I tried for weeks to get anything that would work on its own or that I could get to gel into a bigger structure from smaller riffs, but nothing worked for the heavy section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I also thought I could do kind of a clean intro piece with some noodling solos, perhaps like Testament’s “Musical Dirge” or some of the clean intros they had on other songs on that album. In that vein I played a bit and came up with what you all now know as the clean intro, “Psychosis” - it’s a simple Dm-Abm-Eb5-repeat, with a minor 3-minor-2-root every fourth repeat for the turnaround, that uses my love of simple half-step changes resulting in large chord changes. While the rest of the song languished, I got the intro totally fleshed out. It’s a rhythm that can be played completely in the low-open position and up an octave in the 7th position, and it lends itself well to just being arpeggiated clean or having the arpeggios be played over ringing open distorted chords. I worked out the arrangement for the progression of heaviness and wrote a solo that I was happy with, but then when it ended I didn’t know what to do…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… until I realized that I should have taken my first option with the meat of the song. On a lark I tried just doing a thrash-style gallop on those chords over the open low D and BOOM! - that was the trick. The riff ended up being perfect for the verses - repetitive in a way I like to think goes more towards ‘hypnotic trance’ than ‘unimaginative repeating’ - hammering on the dissonance of the tritone and minor second, along with the ringing chords allowing for bass fills every fourth repeat, makes it nice and compact, and with the song length padded by the intro I could make it a short, fast banger. The chorus part came from just using simple chromatics - it’s the same half-step walkdown as the ‘chorus’ riff in Sabbath’s “Into the Void”, just thrashed up and in a different key (I tune to D, they tuned to C#), with the D-Eb at the very end with a stop leading right back into the next verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had those two parts I just slammed them together - V-C-V-C, with the solo leading to the outro next. For the solo, I kept half the same verse riff, but used riffs to connect the chord alterations (D to C, a good solid minor-key classic for soloing). I tried pulling out all the stops, even going so far as to work in a tapping descending arpeggio which is so far outside of my usual solo wheelhouse it’s not even funny. It worked, though, adding just a bit more difference to the solos on the album as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still not sure how I came up with the ending. I think I had just decided somewhere along the way that I would try to work in bits where I juxtapose major and minor from the same key into the same riff or song, and that’s where the notes I used for those riffs came from - in Dm for the song as a whole, the chords at the end are Gb and F, with A as a single note in between. I liked the sound of the intervals but didn’t know what to do with them, so I thought I’d just slow down and let them ring out, which is exactly what I ended up doing once I heard how it played out. I was also especially happy how the solo blended into that ending progression, since I accidentally just ended up trilling on the same notes. I did that on the demo version, then forgot it, and when I was recording this for the final album version I remember I had to go back and re-figure-out what I had done back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of progression from demo to final version, there was no real change in arrangement, but I did do some playing with instrumentation. On the demo I just did one clean guitar in the low octave for the intro, but I wanted it to have a bit more sparkle, so I used two clean guitar tracks, one playing in the low open position and one an octave higher as I described above. I piled on some chorus and then panned the two tracks hard left and hard right - I think it sounds like you’re inside the middle of a 12-string guitar that way, which is neat while the cleans are playing alone but they still got a bit lost in the mix when the heavy guitars came in. Oh well - it’s a learning process and I’m still overall pretty happy with how this one turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/songs/lyrics-invoking-villainy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/songs/lyrics-invoking-villainy</guid>
        
        <category>Death-Beast</category>
        
        <category>The-Wakening</category>
        
        
        <category>Songs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Not Dead Yet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess I shouldn’t be surprised to be here. After just refreshing myself with my own blog’s history, and thus the numerous times I ‘get back to blogging’ and then let it go months between updates, I shouldn’t be surprised that I did it again, nor should you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it’s that ‘blank page’ syndrome, I guess, combined with the timelessness of this COVID era, that makes it seem like time just melts like ice cream on asphalt on a hot summer day. “What’s one more day to think of where to start?” I tell myself, and then I blink and it’s six weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there’s no cure for it but to just pick up with where I left off. I was telling the story of Death Beast “The Onslaught” (which is now two and a half years old?!?!?) in broad terms while catching people up on songwriting posts about the first album’s songs, which would lead to the second. I guess I also need to cover the ‘live’ album at some point, and maybe Festering Sore’s history as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, all that’s coming. Next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, really.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/meta/not-dead-yet</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/meta/not-dead-yet</guid>
        
        <category>Meta</category>
        
        
        <category>Meta</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OK, NOW We Are Back...</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, as you can see, it took a little longer than I thought to actually get it back online. I thought the website-build irregularities were due to it just being local and not online - instead, it was that all the code was fucked up because I moved it on my local machine and Github’s desktop app and Jekyll in general don’t like things moved after they’re built in a specific place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it took me about a week to figure out how to move things to the right spot, then migrate all the template changes from what I’d done before to the new, properly placed template. Then, of course, Gremlins (as there always seem to be with anything more complicated than an abacus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I’ve defeated all problems and Gremlins and now you can read about this in all its glory. As well as catch up on what I’ve been up to since 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND, bonus for all of you hoping for more frequent updates, this new Jekyll-built markdown blog really IS much easier to post in, now that I’m used to the way the workflow goes, so I should be able to update this more frequently. And, with this gigantic rock out of my shoe, next step - more music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHAT music I’m not sure, but anything’s better than nothing, right? Besides, does anyone out there really like one of my bands and hate the others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Don’t answer that - I’m not sure I want to know…)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/news/ok-now-we-are-back</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/news/ok-now-we-are-back</guid>
        
        <category>Meta</category>
        
        
        <category>News</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We Are Back!!!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sorry for the long delay, but after a year of hand-conversion and learning to program in an entirely new environment, my personal website and blog are now back online. Anyone familiar with my history usually notes that I make big announcements for small changes, tease ‘more info soon’, then drag my feet delivering. I’ll try to break that cycle now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the moment, this is more a proof of concept, since using Jekyll to build my site/blog is new to me, and some of the funcionality I can only test as it’s live, so if this works, then things really SHOULD go more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, we all know what a shitshow 2020 has been, which is when this whole thing first fell apart, just before the whole fucking world did as well. And that’s a story I’m actually eager to tell, as well as catch you up on what a whole year of pandemic has done to the least-hard-working-man in show business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for now, just cross your fingers and hope this works.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/news/we-are-back</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/news/we-are-back</guid>
        
        <category>Meta</category>
        
        
        <category>News</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyrics - Enslaved Cadavers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I was in the middle of working on the six songs that Stan/Dementor gave me for the first Death Beast demo, we were happy enough with what we were working on that we thought we should fill it out to a full album, and so some time later (either later in 2001 or through the earliest part of 2002) he sent me lyrics to two more songs, “Enslaved Cadavers” and “Invoking Villainy”. “Enslaved Cadavers” was the first one in the email so it was the first one I picked to start working on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Thousands of rotting coffins lay empty
Under thousands of tombstones
Paranormal morbidity stirs as
Corpses are reborn to serve

Undead minions of darkness
Fight for their master...
An army of corpses
Enslaved cadavers...

No mortal shall remain alive
Nightmares haunt those who breathe
No escape no matter if you live or die
Blood curdling terror burns deep

Undead minions of darkness
Fight for their master...
An army of corpses
Enslaved cadavers...

Join us...  Join us...
Join us...  Join us...
Join us...  Join us...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure as written pretty much implied the structure of the song - two verse/choruses, a solo section implied, and then an outro. I had done quite a bit of work making the other songs so far pretty involved, arrangement-wise, so I thought a more straightforward song would be okay here. I started by trying to find a riff to hang the song on, and while listening to Slayer’s “Chemical Warfare” I liked how stripped-down and simple the verse riff on that was - no chords except the accent at the start and end and with long-steady strings of single-picked-notes in between. I hammered around and found what you hear now after about a half-hour - true to form, it was a pretty simple Dm-plus-tritone around the open position, with the basic ‘chords’ centering around D and Ab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I broke up the verse feel in the prechorus by going with something that reminds me a bit of those 3-on-2 crunching inverted power chord riffs like Metallica used on Kill ‘em All (the verse to Whiplash, a bit, or more like that pre-chorus thing on No Remorse) - it still uses the open string as a pedal tone, but it sounds a bit like a chord/key change because more focus is put on the accent chords than the pedal. For the chorus I went back to the same notes/chords as the main riff but with a changed feel around a more open drumbeat and ringing chords, plus a quick 16th note chromatic bit at the end plus a dramatic stop at the very end before going back to the verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the solo section I decided to use the stop to preface a key change. I went back to the verse riff but moved it up from D to F (third position) and straight into a solo that followed the same verse-bridge-chorus map in the higher key. At the end of the solo I thought it would be neat to hang on that stop, but with an extended drum fill going down into a more simple outro-type crunchy riff. I straighted out the riff I used for the ‘chorus’ section of the solo (in F) and just worked on a straight-8 pumping, marching drumbeat feel that would be good to fade out on with the ‘join us’ repeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never got a demo of this from Stan so I don’t know what he was going to do with it, so a good deal of the arrangement of this actually came from what Ryan/Juggernaut did on his demos. First, he noticed that I left the quick solo between the two verses shorter than I originally meant to and it ended up being too few words - we needed a new stanza. He wrote one, which you can hear on the demo version of that song on the &lt;em&gt;Prophecies of Doom&lt;/em&gt; compilation (I wrote my own extra stanza, which is what made it to the final version on the album). Ryan’s real genius came through, though, on his idea for the ‘join us’ repeats on the outro. Instead of just going with single repeats or a simple gang chant, he started doing a lot of different versions with different vocal effects that pan around in different spots and start working in extra rhythms in between the main repeats. Though the details are different, the basic idea for what I ended up doing on the final version of the song for the album follows in that same vein. Using the Acid loop-joining/layering program in conjuction with Sound Forge’s manipulations and effects, I recorded a few different versions of me singing/screaming/growling “Join Us”, and then used pitch shifting (up AND down) to generate many different versions of the line, all at tempo with the music. I then took those samples into Acid and layered a steadily building set of repeats, starting with a basic set that repeated on every loop, then adding new samples above and below that repeated every other time, or every four, and with the different up/downshifted samples interspersed with the regular chants. The idea was to have a steadily-growing sound cacophony, like the army of the dead just keeps getting bigger and bigger, and I think it worked out pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/songs/lyrics-enslaved-cadavers</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/songs/lyrics-enslaved-cadavers</guid>
        
        <category>Death-Beast</category>
        
        <category>The-Wakening</category>
        
        
        <category>Songs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Farewell Hartmuth</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: the original post for this was composed completely in Wordpress in September 2019, and was subsequently destroyed by a shitty webhost in January 2020 (of fucking course…). No matter how hard we try sometimes, everything we do will be gone someday, which is the universe’s cruel joke for something supposed to be a memorial. But then I suppose most rites around death are for the living, not the dead, and while we’re still here, &lt;strong&gt;WE&lt;/strong&gt; still remember.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or try to, anyway. I’m rewriting this as of March 2021, some 18 months after the fact, so I’m sure I left some details out. Hopefully the more important truths - that he was a great guy, loved by all, and a dedicated metalhead who played a big, important part of my life - still shine through.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farewell, Hartmuth Schindler, “Opyros”, “Black Goat” - 16 July 1967 - 05 September 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the most important part of that is the dash. That dash is where he made a large, indelible mark on the metal scene that he loved so much. But let’s not forget that’s also where he was son to his parents. Friend to his friends. Husband to his wife, Cheryl. We are all large, and we all contain multitudes. And I count myself incredibly lucky, blessed, even honored, that I’m some small part of that dash up there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember first ‘meeting’ him online around 1998, through ChorazaiM of Megiddo. I found out after working with him to release the Megiddo demo compilation on UHR that Barbarian Wrath had signed him for the next album. Also from ChorazaiM, I first learned of Countess through his reviews of their albums on LARM. Based solely on his recommendation, I went to blackmetal.com (remember them?) and bought &lt;em&gt;Ad Maiorem Sathanae Gloriam&lt;/em&gt; and loved it. I wanted more, and Chor suggested I email Opyros about it. I did, and for the low price of $20 he sent me the other four CDs that Countess had out at the time - &lt;em&gt;Gospel…&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Return of the Horned One&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Book of the Heretic&lt;/em&gt;, and the &lt;em&gt;Hell’s Rock-n-Roll&lt;/em&gt; EP. A few months later I bought the first slew of CDs he had released on his then-brand-spanking-new label, introducing me to Gravewurm and Alastor as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He saw that I did pretty well at running my own UHR online shop, so he didn’t mind helping me stock a few releases, which of course blossomed a few years later when he wanted to give a second run at setting up an official US distro for BW, and he asked if I’d be interested. I jumped at the chance, and to whatever degree anyone outside of my immediate friend circle knows me, it’s likely at least in large part because of the notoriety I gained by being his distributor. It pushed me to work on my own music and my own label releases, and eventually bloomed again when Toby and I decided to try our own hand at a label, thus birthing Alpha Draconis Records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even that, though, doesn’t compare to the boost he gave me when he wanted to sign Death Beast. Of course I had tried to get him to do something with Rampage, but given that Hart was always a guy who liked great lyrics and strong vocal performances, it’s understandable why he didn’t want to do anything with Rampage back when I still had the mic. But that makes his endorsement of Death Beast that much more special - not only did this person, who released so many albums I’d call modern classics, think that something &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; did was worthy of his label, but he was also the person instrumental in giving me the push to say “fuck it, I’ll do the vocals myself”. One of my proudest accomplishments is getting &lt;em&gt;The Wakening&lt;/em&gt; up to the standard that he felt was worthy of Barbarian Wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, tied with that, one of my greatest regrets is that I didn’t get &lt;em&gt;The Onslaught&lt;/em&gt; done quickly enough for him to hear it in all its hellish glory. He had heard scratch tracks and test mixes of the whole thing, up to perhaps a 70% stage of completion (missing maybe a few backing vocals or guitar solos), and I know he liked what he heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that still doesn’t get to Hartmuth himself. He was funny, and opinionated, and charming. Chatting online with him about everything and nothing was great when it was every day (back in the days of AIM and instant messaging), trading emails. We even talked on the phone a couple of times - once I remember when my oldest son was still a baby. I was there feeding him and trying to get him to sleep, balancing the phone on my shoulder so I could talk and feed at the same time while he regaled me with tales of his trip to the US (the one where he did The Cannonball Run!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a lot of people knew him a lot better than I did, but I still think of him as a friend, and I’d like to think he did the same as well. I’ll miss you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/history/farewell-hartmuth</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/history/farewell-hartmuth</guid>
        
        <category>Eulogy</category>
        
        
        <category>History</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyrics - Every Church Shall Burn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Every Church Shall Burn” was kinda the ‘bastard child’ of the first six songs that Stan/Dementor sent me in Summer of 2001. As you can see from the lyrics, they don’t scan in a regular rhythm, there are odd line counts, and the overly-long repeated section doesn’t really lend itself well to what we would think of as a chorus. As I described before, I left this one for last, and so it’s the only one of those first six that Dementor never did a demo of - though he tried, and based on what I ended up writing it was confusing on paper because I distinctly remember him emailing me and saying he wasn’t sure what I wanted him to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;They call me a blasphemer, call me a lecher
I call 'em fools, mindless sheep, worthless beggars
I shall indulge every sin, rebel until I die
I shall reject their book of lies
It's hypocritical content is only god for one act
Take your holy bible, and wipe your shit-soaked ass...

...I blaspheme thy holy chapel
Make the nuns suck my dick...
Perversion of the Holy Virgin
Inversion of the Crucifix...
...Sadistic, scourging thy wife brings me pleasure
Psychopathic, I laugh as I slit the priest's throat...
I'll thrust the Devil's unholy trident
Up the mother Mary's cunt...

So the idiots call me sick
Say I should be imprisoned
When the time comes to kill
You shall all know my reasons
The bastards are stupid, they drive me insane
One day some of them shall feel the edge of my blade...

...I blaspheme thy holy chapel
Make the nuns suck my dick...
Perversion of the Holy Virgin
Inversion of the Crucifix...
...Sadistic, scourging thy wife brings me pleasure
Psychopathic, I laugh as I slit the priest's throat...
I'll thrust the Devil's unholy trident
Up the mother Mary's cunt...

As the Virgin's hymen is torn...
As the Antichrist is born...
As the end of time dawns...
Every church shall burn...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a thrash band, I wanted to work in at least one slower song, harkening back to the way that older thrash, death, and black metal would use slow or midpaced songs to break up the constant-speed feel. Since we had covered Slaughter on the demo, my natural thought was to come up with something that had a similar feel to one of their slower songs, perhaps along the lines of “Tales of the Macabre” or “Fuck of Death”. I already had the main F-B tritone riff just sitting around (when I first came up with it, I was thinking it was a bit like Darkthrone, in the vein of their simpler old-school songs like “In the Shadow of the Horns”), but when I changed the last chord in it (sliding up to Ab) from a power chord to just a vibratoed single note it sounded a lot more like Slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I just came up with a couple of basic variations of the riff, figuring on stringing them together like “Verse part A, Verse part B”, and varying the lengths until I could come up with a vocal line that fit the repeats of the riffs properly. I also tacked on that direct quote of Slaughter as the intro just for Hartmuth to smile at, and since anything worth doing is worth overdoing I also pretty early on decided to also do that trademark Slaughter “One Two Fuck You” count-in. Since the repeated part didn’t work quite so well as a traditional chorus I decided to treat it like a verse with a different riff, so a couple of hours repeating the lines over the prospective guitar riffs helped me hammer out the arrangement. I added the quick key change up to Ab between the two verses just to break up the arrangement a bit, and then when it came to the solos I thought it would be a good idea to keep up the variation by having two different riff styles in different keys with the tradeoffs - I kept one of the verse riffs for one of the solo riffs and then had a step-down new riff in low D for the other. Those solos were fun trading off, because I had just bought the wah pedal you all hear me abuse now and this was my first time giving it a workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, I wasn’t sure how to get back to that four-line stanza at the end, but I thought even after all of the variations up to this point it was still basically just a slow song and some kind of thrash or more upbeat bit would be best. I stuck with the original key of F and came up with a new uptempo riff, then figured it would be good to repeat the ‘chorus’ there so that it didn’t sound like just a tacked-on bit. It also helped that riding out of the end of that chorus gave me a way to bring the song full circle back to the original main riff of the song, which ended up being a perfect way to put that last stanza to some music. I felt at that point that the riff could just repeat to a fadeout, but with slightly changing drumbeats and basslines under it, slowly building in intensity. I ended up leaving the space for the last stanza at double the length it needed, so I had to write a few more lines to fill it out properly - if you’ve read the lyrics on the album (or online) you know what parts I added.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/songs/lyrics-every-church-shall-burn</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/songs/lyrics-every-church-shall-burn</guid>
        
        <category>Death-Beast</category>
        
        <category>The-Wakening</category>
        
        
        <category>Songs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lyrics - Agent of the Reaper</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Agent of the Reaper” was the fifth of the original six Death Beast songs that I wrote, though it was last in the email. Song five, “Every Church Shall Burn”, had such a weird structure that I bypassed it so that I could finish an easier one first and keep the momentum going. If you’ve seen the demo tracklists, though, you know by now that this song never ended up on the original four-song demo, even though it could have been (though I guess that would have made it a five-song demo - plus covers… but I digress). I had a drum and music synchronization problem that crept in as I was in the middle of converting between two different software platforms - either two versions of Cakewalk (7.0 and 9.0) or between Cakewalk 9.0 and Sonar 1.2. The other demo songs didn’t have this problem, and it’s been so long now that I can’t remember the details. That said, I DO have a recorded version of this with Stan/Ironfist on vocals, but the drums are so out-of-sync that it’s pretty unlistenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What he gave me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vrs.
They call me Demetor; the Destroyer; the Demon
They call me a killer, Agent of the Reaper
For when you least expect it, early in your life
A shadowy figure stalks you and you're murdered by my knife
Before the Reaper takes you, if He thinks you should die instantly
He raises up his scepter, and to slay he summons me

Agent of the Reaper...
Executioner of the Worthless
Agent of the Reaper...
Bringer of Diabolical murder
Agent of the Reaper...
Slayer of youthful mortals
Agent of the Reaper...
I am your Destroyer!

(mid song bridge type thing:)
In the shadows I lurk
In the dead of the night...
When you hear my footsteps
You shall die of fright...
And when you feel me, getting near...
Nothing shall save you, as you drown in fear...
And then I will strike, send you down to Hell
Slit your jugular vein, at Death's command...

(repeat vrs. chs.)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the other songs that Stan recorded for the Death Beast demo, he sang this one pretty much the way I envisioned when I wrote it, which is pretty much the way you’ve heard it on all of the other versions that are out there. His notes about verses, bridges, and choruses suggested the structure, and with a single verse repeating fore and aft I thought it would do well as an album-ending superfast thrasher, along the lines of “Hardening of the Arteries”, “Strike of the Beast”, or “Nailed to the Cross”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember starting with the drumbeat on this one. I was worried about the other songs being too ‘stiff’ with fast but rigid beats, so with this one I started with one of those fast, staggered 16ths-note beats that you can cram a few full-four-16ths in: dotted eighth, sixteenth, two eighths, and repeat, sometimes dropping four-sixteenths instead of the dotted-note combo. It doesn’t scan in text as well as it sounds, so just listen to the drum intro and you’ll hear what I mean. It reminded me of a lot of the kinds of fast, simple, heavy rhythms that the guys would write back when I was in Skiptoe, and so I went for a pretty straight, direct, Dm-plus-tritone progression for the main riff. On the demo I grinded on the low “D” power-chord in the open position, but after that when I started working it up for the proper album I thought it sounded a bit more classic-old-school thrash to hit the higher D in the 7th position (like those old E-based Metallica riffs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest just flowed from trying to keep the fast feeling through the verses - not changing the tempo or beat too much, but using different kinds of riffs for each section. The regular thrash-styled ‘3-on-4’ riff for the verse changed to a combined riff of ringing chords under a muted 16th-note riff, then a different staccato riff for the chorus that combined chugging with accent chords. Instead of chugging on just a low ‘D’ I alternated D and F, another thing that harkened back to the Skiptoe days. Changing to the slow ‘mosh’ part for the bridge was a given, and again it just kinda wrote itself, along with the way the song flowed back to the chorus riff for the solo, then used the verse turnaround to come back to the main riff. I wish I could still make them fall together this easily nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/songs/lyrics-agent-of-the-reaper</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/songs/lyrics-agent-of-the-reaper</guid>
        
        <category>Death-Beast</category>
        
        <category>The-Wakening</category>
        
        
        <category>Songs</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>